so this is a
suitor called the simile of the
poisonous snakes
or vipers
because suppose there were four vipers
of fierce heat and deadly venom
then a man would come along wanting to
live not wanting to die
desiring happiness and adverse to
suffering they would tell him good man these four
they would tell him good man these four
vipers
are a fierce heat and deadly venom from
time to time they must be lifted up
from time to time they must be bathed
from time to time they
must be fed and from time to time they
must be laid
to rest but if one or another of these
vipers ever becomes angry with you then good
ever becomes angry with you then good
man you will meet death or deadly
suffering do whatever has to be done
a little bit later on in the discourse
says i have made up the simile because
in order to convey a meaning
this is the meaning here before vipers
are fierce heat and deadly venom this is
the designation for the
four great elements earth water heat
and air
they're saying he's you know he's not
saying those are like
beautiful energy that you must connect
with and appreciate
and cultivate those energies so that you
can you're saying these are poisonous
deadly vipers like this killer the wind
you can look up that's the thing with
snakes you can that's why they will give
that simile
you can look after you can bathe you can
feed and they can still bite you because they
and they can still bite you because they
have no concept of what you're doing
so you can do everything right in other
words and still get bitten
it's not like you know dog will bite you
when he's upset
or a laugher will attack you if he's
threatened the snake will just bite you and
the snake will just bite you and
misperceives you or whatever even if you
you're feeding it and bathing it and
looking after it
so that's why it's a similar like oh the
man would still like be scared
oh these these vipers need to be lifted
up
cleaned fed bathed
yeah they might bite you so so you'll be
scared because there is no
guarantee that you will not get bitten
even if you do everything right
to all your exercises in other words
it's not
yeah yeah it's not in your control you
can do everything right and still die on
account of it
and what is the fourth grade element
what is the
the closest
thing to you that is made out of four
great elements
in your body yeah entirely entirely not
the parts of your body and then there
are other
parts of it that are yours your body in
its entirety
are the four vipers so the four
whimsical elements that you don't really
exist for so to speak that's a thing
like snake doesn't have awareness of you
as it's carrier feeder it's literally
just it sees what's in the front it reacts it
it sees what's in the front it reacts it
acts you change and you you cannot
connect to it like form a relationship with it
to it like form a relationship with it
like even even people who actually do
have snakes whose pets they look after
them one wrong move and you can get bitten
one wrong move and you can get bitten
because it's not there's no no
perception of it in the snake
so there's no perception in the four
great elements
of you that did oh he is a master or
he's our basically our friend or an
individual we are bound with not at all
they have their own course
and you are paired with the body that is
comprised of four grade elements
for as long as their body is there
basically doing its own thing
when that changes you will not be able
to remain
no matter how friendly you are no matter
what how much you look after it no
matter the extent of your
ownership yeah exactly you know you know
you can't prevent it
you can't prevent it but it's
it seems to be that's the perception you
should be developing
towards us well you have to because
unless for as long as you're seeing your own
for as long as you're seeing your own
body the elements that are comprising it
in friendly terms
you're not going to be seeing the danger
by not seeing the danger you will remain
infatuated and assuming the ownership of it that's
and assuming the ownership of it that's
just the result of
not seeing the danger so if you start
regarding it as deadly vipers
whereby there is no wrong move that you
can do
and they'll still kill you they still
might kill you at any given time
they're being completely unaware that
they're killing you they'll just do it
as in even the concept of you dying
means nothing to them
then you would you would be you what you
would think twice before you regard that
as friendly
and in mind and and worth
finding joy and using it for pursuit of
pleasure contemplate those elements
you know what are you supposed to be
looking for like is it well
well you shouldn't yeah what you
shouldn't be doing is
starting with your idea of elements and
then applying it to you because it's
already going to be misconceived
so you want to you want to do it
you want to find or discern the elements
within first discerning the proper phenomenon
first discerning the proper phenomenon
of your body for what it is
so recognizing certain facticity of the
body and then within that discerning these
and then within that discerning these
characteristics of
solid um liquid firearm
just again as properties of the body
because of which
body is there so not not optional
i can see like this or i can know these
four things are to be cultivated because
by discerning these four properties of
this body you get to discern that the
universal properties of anything that
appears anything that appears shares the
anything that appears shares the
property of solid liquid area firing
so that's how you would then realize
that this
tiny body less than two meters tall in
comparison you know to the mountains and
seas and oceans
is made of the same elements literally
and you could see like how much wind
blows and rains and
uh earthquakes and landslides and trees
falling and mountains crumbling
what is then to expect of this tiny
quite precious precarious little kind of
precious precarious little kind of
compound of flesh which is made of
exactly the same elements
like the world around you world around
you that you see constantly changing and
crumbling and disintegrating and forming
and reforming
so contemplating seeing these
characteristics of the greater universal
nature of
form deforming that is in its nature
but you can see that on the level of
idea of
visualization and and that's not it you
need to see
through the body that is yours
to begin with because that's how then
that seeing it in the right order
will basically undermine your sense of
ownership of that body
if you're just seeing it in the level of
theory it's you're not undermining
anything you again you're just sort of
you again you're just sort of
contemplating fantasizing theoretically
but if you first okay this body here
seated position
breathing having degree of warmth degree
of solidity
cohesion whatever you want to describe
these characteristics
and then allow those characteristics to
endure because even that in itself you
realize oh that body is given to you the way the
oh that body is given to you the way the
way you're seeing it
in in other words you you you cannot
kind of
go behind it and have a say in its
creation or its persistence
it's there but it can also not be there
if it decides to die or something
happens to it
so no amount of your control in tension
volition can step outside and go and
kind of repossess that body
externally and truly become the only
master of it
it's always secondary to it if you
pursue that same contemplation
that kind of impenetrable nature of the
body on account of which your whole life
depends then you already are discerning the the
then you already are discerning the the
characteristics of the four elements
which are pretty much
impenetrable like you you cannot i mean
can you literally can you even conceive
can you find stopping the wind stopping
the air from moving i mean is that
you can't you can't even imagine that
like it would be ridiculous
and yeah that's exactly what your body
is made of the same characteristics of
the same wind
of the same heat or getting angry
yeah well yeah getting angry getting
lustful all of that requires that basis of
all of that requires that basis of
assumed ownership first
so you can use that as a as a symptom as
an um
indication or am i getting angry am i
getting lustful if so
means i'm not really uh contemplating
the body on the right terms
because if i were to do so i would not
be
uh prone to lust or aversion you just
couldn't you wouldn't be able to give
into anger or
or attraction to something that's going
to kill you
that can kill that which is kind of
completely outside of your scope
even of of in imaginary control if you
look at it closely the clearly it
becomes you realize you can't even
feather how it would be the only reason
you you assume
the ownership and the sense of control
over the bodies because you never really
ever think about the nature of oh this
is
this is inaccessible to me
but the more you think about it the less
you'll be able to then drift away
in those assumptions of ownership but
it's unpleasant
from the point of view of ownership the
sense of non-ownership
is fearful and frightening it's scary
so that's why like again people would
need to
have had some sense restraint concealer
develop beforehand
otherwise you're just going to be
filling yourself with anxiety and you
will not
know how to deal with it
because you haven't um you haven't
developed strength on account of
restraining your behavior
beforehand
so that's why you have to regard it as
deadly vipers
everything like shorter than that will
still could still have lingering
attitudes of
friendliness and ownership towards it oh
okay it's not
you know you know i i i if i do the
right things you know
i'm in control of these vipers no you're
never in control of the vipers
balancing the energies no no you're
literally just just balancing when you're gonna
just just balancing when you're gonna
get bitten
so so that's the record you have to
that's why good man do what you think
it's it's the right thing to do oh well
the right thing is to leave these vipers
and run from my life
yes
that similarly continues then because
afraid of the four vipers of fierce heat
and deadly venom
that man would flee in one direction or
another they would tell him good man five
they would tell him good man five
murderous enemies are pursuing you
thinking wherever we see him we'll take
his life
right on the spot do whatever has to be
done good man
and that's it
there are five murderous enemies this is
a designation for the five aggregates
subject to assumption form feeling
perception determinations consciousness
these are the five murderous enemies
so there you go now you could you can
you can practice that
seeing the danger in the four elements
so you you develop
disenchantment towards the form and
anything that comes out of it um
um
or you can then carry on and do the same
towards uh perception feeling
uh perception feeling
intentions like other aspects like you
can you can easily overlook okay well
this is not physical this is not
material you know certain significance of some
you know certain significance of some
feelings
ideas notions mind you it's always
physical you wouldn't have those things
if you don't have the form
but nevertheless you know the mind can
can sort of
find its ways of
keeping its ignorance feeling it
so you want to you want to reflect
further okay so if if you approach it
through the five aggregates
you think you outran the four great
elements because you withdraw from the
attachment to the body maybe but how
about now attachment to your intentions
things you want to do things you feel
things you perceive do you enjoy
perceiving even if it's effortless even
if you're not seeking out
these perceptions do you still enjoy the
fact that you can perceive
are you still bound with that
so all these things that come as a
result of those four great elements paid
the consciousness
the five aggregates they're the
murderous enemies
so even if you withdraw yourself from
the from the four snakes
now you're on the run from the five
hired assassins high murderers they're
seeking out to kill you
on the spot so if if you get to meet
these five yeah how would you
what would your attitude be towards them
hey how's it going let's let's talk
about this
there literally is no talk he said
they'll kill you on sight will they see
you they'll kill you
well you don't so you will hide you
would not even want to be seen
by form by feeling by perception by
intention by consciousness
let alone engage with it let alone try
to reason with it
being seen means getting killed
so next time there is a lingering
feeling of something
that you're acting out of can you act
out of a feeling
if that feeling doesn't even see you if
you make sure you do not
present yourself to that feeling you
don't take it up you don't engage you
don't lay yeah i'm here i'm here you
keep it at the distance
you keep yourself at distance from the
feet from there isn't feeling you can't
keep the feeling in the distance the
murderous assassins they they go as they
please and come and seek you
so you can't keep yourself at a distance
so they don't kill you
so the hiding place from the aggregates
he's keeping yourself at a distance what
is that how do you do it
how do you keep yourself well but not
not acting out of it to begin with by
not welcoming the assassin into your
home but not seeking out and trying to to
but not seeking out and trying to to
fight back
by not not pretending that oh no he's
not you're not go like we will talk
about it that's fine
doesn't feel exactly well that's that's
usually how the the
like if somebody wants to kill you
that's usually how it will work who
lure you out that's the whole that's the
whole premise of a bait so
premise of a bait so
so the you would make yourself unknown
for the feeling for the intention for
the consciousness
for the aggregates
so you have your experience at home
whatever that is whatever mood is
enduring whatever feeling is enduring whatever
whatever feeling is enduring whatever
like pressure
towards action to what sensuality to
deal with is enduring
you don't try to get rid of that that
would be like trying to chase away
the murder the five murderers
so you don't try to get rid of it and
you certainly don't
okay i'll just do what they tell me to
because that results in your death and
they say come out come out of hiding
we're not gonna harm you come out of
hiding and you come out of hiding
so you don't act out of it you don't try
to get rid of it because that will also
give away your position
so you have to allow it to endure and by
allowing it to endure
and not acting out of it you get to
understand the nature of it
and certainly if you still had any
notions of control over your feelings
intentions and aggregates
you will not because now you realize any
form of
being known or recognized by these
things means death
means liability to death to suffering
your whole experience you're surrounded
by
a danger yeah
literally like not even um
not even like you're surrounded i mean
figuratively speaking i understand but
the point is
don't think that you have the like a
sixth place where you can hide
from these five murderers no
five murderers are your five stepping
stones so you're always on someone's
murdering fields
right right through your whole
experience so then the only way to hide is to
so then the only way to hide is to
basically
like literally remove the ownership let
go of it make yourself invisible
towards whatever pressure is there
enduring in you
because that's really the problem the
people keep acting out of
being contacted being pressured that's
that's that's
the root of all problems for every
individual if you were not acting out these things
if you were not acting out these things
would not deceive you then even more
so whatever feeling you have towards
like anger frustration you don't act out
because that's always the problem when
the problem does arise is after people
acted out
if you were not acting if you were not
committing come on account of these
things they will these things will not
see you
they will just come threaten shout try
to pressure you towards action or lure
you out with sensuality
uh sort of enchant you with beautiful
sight sounds smell taste touches all of
that but still if you were not choosing to
but still if you were not choosing to
step into that
bait domain of bait domain of a trap
these things cannot possess forever they
would move on but it's usually an
individual who cannot bear that pressure bear that
who cannot bear that pressure bear that
pull bear that enchantment
so that's the problem really now you can
say okay so i'll just never act out of
these things
that's fine but these things are so
deeply rooted it's simply saying no to
it
and enduring it you have to start like
that but then you really you need wisdom as
but then you really you need wisdom as
well in order to be able to to actually
fulfill not acting out of it
but then wisdom yeah for that you need
instruction as we said in previous talks
but at the same time no amount of
instruction unless you're restrained
first unless your senses are restrained as in
unless your senses are restrained as in
you are restrained in regard to your
senses normal wisdom can take place even if the
normal wisdom can take place even if the
buddha himself is teaching you there
step by step so you do need to be
restrained you do need to at least
out of a principle not act when you're
pressured by pleasure by pain by neutral feeling
so see you're already emulating act
like non-acting you're already emulating
being invisible
to the murderers and once you get to
understand then it becomes even easier then you
then it becomes even easier then you
actually learn that there is this whole
way of you can move around
without being seen and what often says
that mata can't see you
develop the right view practice fair
beneficiarity become american you're
invisible mark cannot see you yeah what
it means
in marriage that's fine though five
aggregators six senses whatever
everything is matter everything that
appears belongs tomorrow
so if you're engaging with it you're
engaging with modest possessions so he
has every right to do whatever he wants
with you
because you you do it willingly
grab the bait willingly you go after it
so then afraid of the four vipers of
fierce heat and deadly venom and
and of the five murderous enemies that
man would flee in one direction or
another the italian good man a sixth murderer
the italian good man a sixth murderer
an intimate companion is pursuing you
with a drawn sword
thinking wherever i see him i'll cut off
his head right on the spot
do whatever has to be done good man
and that's the sixth murderer the
intimate companion withdrawn sword
this is the designation for delight and
lust delights
exactly so you see it's getting softer
and subtler
right so you can okay i see the peril of
the four vipers
i see the peril of the of the of these
five murderers
but still it's even harder than
it's even subtler than to see the peril
of your own
delight towards
anything pretty much however subtle it
might be in your experience
and that's exactly what i was saying so
it's like when you
you choose to accept pleasure you choose
to accept pain and try to get rid of it
you choose to try to distract yourself
from mutual feeling carelessly
and that delight that arises in regards
to these feelings
that's even such a thing you need to see
as dangerous
as in your own intention to give in is
the most dangerous thing because that
that's that's always quoted in that delight how
that's always quoted in that delight how
does the light result in
always because delightful
means friendly delightful means
agreeable non-threatening friendly means not
non-threatening friendly means not
dangerous because it's friendly
well again imagine seeing a good friend
delightful a delightful person there's nothing to
a delightful person there's nothing to
fear in regard to this person
so that's what we're compared to
intimate companion so it's
the closest friendly phenomena you
regard yourself
for yourself your own delight which is
actually completely there on a on a false
completely there on a on a false
pretense
as your friend he's just there to kill
you
so that delight that always results in
you giving in to this or that
because you don't see the danger on
account of delight
if you were to not do that would you
have to worry about the vipers of the
five murderers
it's the delight that always sends you
back to them carelessly
because if you are not delighting in
anything you'll never make yourself
known or visible
to the murderers and you know you would
have to look after the vipers
that's the doorway that's that's pretty
much that
they can everything around you can be
bait set by mara but none of that bait can
set by mara but none of that bait can
pounce and
bait you by itself you are always the
one who makes that first and the last step
who makes that first and the last step
towards it
so if you were to learn to live
surrounded by the bait
and simply remove the slightest delight
in engaging with the bait
that's it you're free hunter cannot see
you because
he can only see you once you're trapped
he comes and checks the beethoven look
there is
but if you never catch the baited oh
this bait is useless you learn
how to live around the bait so you're
trying to find where
where is that delight how can i be
mindful of the light
well see that's already well if you want
to be mindful of the light first be
mindful of the four vipers
then be mindful of the five five
murderers then you can see what's left
there it's
your delight you can't just
attention towards well exactly that
intention that's rooted in seeing non-danger
that's rooted in seeing non-danger
or not seeing danger
so are there things like okay so your
sense restrained
you're celibate you're moderating eating
all that's great all that's building up
but now
you sit a lot alone in the solitude
other things you delight in
as in oh let me let me go for a
delightful walk
is it done with the delight the walk is
not a problem if there's a purpose but
it's a problem if it's done out of the
light if you're delighting in it
oh let me go to sleep am i sort of
joyful on account of the prospect of
sleeping
you you know you know you know
not like i'll never sleep or i never
walk again because everything is
centrality no
it's your delight that's the problem
walking is not central but if you do it
out of delight
yeah you still keep yourself bound with
essential domain and other things even
if you remain perfectly restrained
for the rest of your life if you want to
uproot sensuality
and that whole peril that comes with it
the light is that gateway
they must be shot it sounds quite
depressing but it does it does you're
surrounded by fighters
enemies well it's only depressing
because your mind still wants things to
be otherwise
i mean like you wouldn't be depressed if
i tell you two and two is four
that's just yeah that's just how it is
two and two is four
only if you strongly wish for 202 to be
six you'll be depressed to find out that
two and two is four
so you're not depressed because 22 is
four you're depressed because of your
own misconceived expectations so if you're
misconceived expectations so if you're
depressed on account of the vipers and
the factual murderers
and stuff well yeah it's because you're
ignoring it because you want things to
be different
things that are not in your control you
want to be different
so you yourself make yourself depressed
but the light is
yeah it delights exactly you delight in
these other ideas that are contradictory
to
reality of things so if you remove that
there is no
like arahant he's joyless
he has no delight yet that's the
greatest joy in the world
once you develop it the safety across
the shore
you cannot be happy because you're
surrounded by always factually again
it's not optional
oh if i don't think about this if i
don't read these suitors these murderers
will not come
no we're telling you how what you are
what your life is what the aggregates
are describing the nature from a greater
describing the nature from a greater
perspective that
from somebody who developed it so yeah
you can ignore it
and then literally be like like
the the easiest prey
or you can try and do something about it
which is that's always
okay good man do what you think is fit
oh it's fit to try and avoid this
yeah that's true because that's the
thing if you admit it you realize the
only fit thing to do is to
to try and overcome this and then he he
keeps running hiding and he's okay i
have to hide further
further and further so the intimate
companion that's what it is you need to recognize
that's what it is you need to recognize
the most intimate point of view that you
have that delight that comes with it
with your intentions
even things like okay the things that
are obviously harmful
but not even things that are not harmful
you're not against the priesthood and
stuff are you delighting
mentally in it it's that the light is
the heart
is the danger and it's hard to see
because that
has always been with you that's always
the closest to you that's always in the
heart of every intention
that you act out of delight my my
trustworthy friend
since the day i was born i noticed this
friend of delight
and yet now he found out oh yeah he's
there also to kill you
that was his sole purpose all this time
just cut your head off
afraid of the four vipers of fierce heat
and deadly venom the five
murderous enemies and the sex murderer
the intimate companion withdrawn
sword that man would flee in one
direction or another
he would he would see an empty village
whatever house he enters is void
deserted and empty whatever party takes
hold is void hollow and empty
they would tell him good man just now
village attackers will raid
this empty village do whatever has to be
done good man
and the empty village this is the
designation for the six
internal sense bases if beku's a wise
competent intelligent person examines
them by way of the eye
and so on they appear to be void hollow
and empty
yeah yeah so if you
that's not even subtler well don't rest
on that
either because that which is void hollow
empty unownable that you have hidden away from
unownable that you have hidden away from
all these previous murderous vipers and
intimate companions
well that also is about to be raided and
swept away in a stampede of
of robbers and maniacs so better
keep moving keep moving
so from the delight moving away from you
yeah so you uploaded the delight
but you still rest upon the hollowness
that's like what we spoke in a few talks
ago about non-being
like not the light it's it's not the
delight that you have to being but still
you the the fact that you are resting that
the the fact that you are resting that
you're not moving further away that
you're not seeing the danger even of
that hollow
unownable things that you have no
delight in
means to that extent there is still that
arupaba that we spoke about
the the non-material so to speak being
that you are that you exist in in that
form so there's no delight there
which is why often even um in the suttas
he could could just not he he would
think he's another hunt
overestimate himself there are a number
of cases in the sutures
because things are so subtle now there's
no delays no sensuality
nothing really from the world can harm
you and you're fully confident you fully
and you're fully confident you fully
recognize that see it for yourself
but there is the point that yeah okay
see now there's deep down inside the
holiness all that that you understood
abandon that as well
because that too will be swept away and
to that extent you will be exposed to
suffering in peril
but by all means everybody who is still
dealing with the vipers find an empty
village you'll be safe there
relatively speaking in comparison you'll
be safe
eventually abandon that as well
but not before you have abandoned
everything else that's actively seeking
out to destroy you
well okay sorry i'll say the village
attackers this is a designation for the six
this is a designation for the six
external sense places
so that the eye is attacked by agreeable
and disagreeable forms yeah
it's it's still as i say it's still
pressured even if you're not acting out
not delighting it's still being harassed
by it and sooner or later it will be
destroyed by the world so to that extent you are
by the world so to that extent you are
you there yeah
yeah well it doesn't matter if it's
agreeable disagreeable the fact that
there are sights for the eyes
that's disturbing itself
so you can't then prevent well you
already know that otherwise you wouldn't
be in an empty village
you can't prevent science melted
structures from besetting
and attacking and harassing the other
it's in
internal counterparts but you can
certainly then
remove even the subtlest notion of
resting upon those internal counterparts
and then you will not be disturbed
not exactly not attacked by it yeah
so then because afraid of the four
vipers of fierce heat
deadly venom and five murderous enemies
and of the sixth murder the intimate
companion withdrawn sword
and the village attackers that man would
flee in one direction
or another he would see a great expanse
of water
whose near shore was dangerous and
fearful and whose further shore was safe
and free from danger
but there would be no ferry boats or
bridge for crossing over
from the near shore to the far shore
then the man would think there is this
great expanse of water whose near shore
is dangerous and fearful and whose very
further shore is safe and free from
danger but there is no ferry boat or
bridge for crossing over
let me collect grass twigs branches and
foliage and bind them together into a raft so
and bind them together into a raft so
that by means of that draft making an
effort with my hands and feet i sail
into nebar
yeah i i can get to safely across that
far shore and but this is
and being crossed over gone beyond the
brahman stands on high ground
and that's always said for another hunt
that's he's the only one that's thoroughly
he's the only one that's thoroughly
fully reached the safety
in this very life the great expanse of
water is a designation for the four floods
is a designation for the four floods
sensuality
father views ignorance
yes you must cross it all you can cross
two or half or third of it
or half or third of it
you need to cross the hole you know you
can even be
very close to the other shore but you're
still not from there
it's still not safe even if you're like
two meters away from the
safe shore and all the way you left the
back the bad show
no you're in you're still you're still
not
you're still not safe and that near sure
which is dangerous and fearful is a
designation for
identity
this assumption of mind assumption of
mind ownership
i am sense of self just
whichever way you take it that's what it
is that's where that's what identifies
you that's what defines you
they're near right here yes
that's me like through that you see even
with that delight that's already kind of
in the heart of your being
delight that that kind of energy for
life that you have pretty much
that's already affected with the light
so how can you abandon delight and not
lose energy for life
so by seeing the danger of it that's
like the um
that uh arahant in terra terrigata
said i delight not in life i delight not
in death
i await my time like hilling his wage as
in i completed my work
i'm waiting for a reward for the payment
of pardon ivana
so he doesn't want to die but he
certainly doesn't want to live either
because life means engaging with the
vipers life means engaging with the
murderous
sort of assassins
means means definitely disagreeable
disagreeable pressure
that whole thing it's a mess it's it's
truly apparel
so you realize there is absolutely
nowhere that you can rest upon no absolutely no
that you can rest upon no absolutely no
room
to set your foot that you are kind of
safe here unless you abandon it all
and that's same for this life or like if
you if you um if you look at it from the
if you um if you look at it from the
point of view of samsara
every single time it's always like that
so constant constant peril
from every direction and you are the one
ignoring it
not like these things are not there to
be seen and understood
now you are choosing to look away and
pretend it's not there
and that's why beings due to their own
actions keep themselves bound like that
keep themselves bound like that
reappearance constantly wandering around
roaming around
that shore of samsara where everything
is just out to get you
and all because you don't see the danger
if you see the danger you would not
delight in it it would not be possible
to delight
if the further shore which is safe and
free from danger this is the designation
for nibana
the raft is a noble eightfold path
making effort with hands and feet this
is the arousing of energy
and by the way you you could even just
immediately skip the other bits and start making
skip the other bits and start making
your raft as soon as you realize about
the vipers
yeah that's us yeah you don't need to
wait but they will describe the whole process
but they will describe the whole process
and as he as he was describing that
the empty villagers the man with wisdom
with this sermon would see that which
means without most people would not even
see you don't even know what internal sense
you don't even know what internal sense
bases are
so either of these things yeah if you
can great if you already have wisdom to
discern it great
but either of these things that is the
vipers the five murderers the intimate
companion it's it's it's enough for you to want to
it's it's it's enough for you to want to
seek the other show
so start making your act as soon as you
realize that danger don't spend your
time seeking safety on that shore because as
seeking safety on that shore because as
i said you know five murderers
five murderers are relatively relatively
safer than the
four vipers an intimate companion is
relatively safer
than five murderers and four vipers
it's subtler an empty village is
relatively safer than an intimate
companion but either way you're still on that
but either way you're still on that
shore and one way or the other you will
be killed by something
so you better abandon it and if you
start abandoning it then
you'll you'll be going through all these
um i don't say stages because these are
similes they're not necessarily stages
but you would be
even if on account of vipers you want to
practice the dharma
build a raft and cross into safety you
will get to see the the relative safety of
get to see the the relative safety of
the internal
internal bases the the relative safety
of
of just the delight if i control the
light if i don't give in to the light
i'm safe
but all of that is still on that
dangerous pedal ashore
so the point is to to actually seek all
the way out
because often would happen even in the
even those who did understand the dharma
they would stop perceiving the danger
sufficiently enough
and then would not become arahants not
at least in this life
and that's what would you say like if
you meet the saudi banner he would urge
them like basically stare at a sense of
like basically stare at a sense of
urgency may scare them
scare them literally why because they
still have work to do
they still haven't abandoned the village
they still haven't abandoned the delight
yeah they abandoned the vipers they
probably abandoned the great deal of
five murderers
they understood the nibana they
understood the escape to the other show
but they haven't abandoned it fully so
he would scare them
if he would meet sakuragami or anagami
he would also
cause a raw sense of urgency in them why
because they still have work to do if
you meet another hundred he wouldn't
why because he doesn't have work to do
and aaron's the only one who actually
crossed
he crossed over gone beyond the brahman
stands on high ground
as the designation for the earth
yeah so as depressing as it might sound
it's actually good news because the
sooner you realize the danger
well the sooner you start uploading your
own delight because of which you're
exposed to the danger
you're not exposed to the danger because
of the danger
you're exposed to danger because you
keep exposing yourself to the danger
that's out there
so it's dangerous to you because you
keep going there you stop going there
it says things the murderers are there
but now
they're not danger to you because they
can't see you that's the joy
they've been coming that's the truth
that you are actually safe from the
state because by the way safety is the uh
because by the way safety is the uh
the kind of underlying wish
underlying project even when you do
engage with these things you do it
because you want that outcome of
satisfaction peace non-disturbance
safety even when you engage with
centrality even when you try to
angrily get rid of something it's always
because you want that outcome of
i don't want to be bothered so if you
truly recognize that
it's the universal goal of every
individual to not be bothered to be at
ease which it is the goal then you realize
which it is the goal then you realize
okay so now i have a choice how i go
about it
do i go by acting out of these things
and hoping ease will come
or do i actually start thinking thinking
about it
on a deeper level and see actually
there's something else i can do
that is different to these obviously uh
insufficient attempts because you know
the best case scenario in in the life of
centrality non-restraining is a very very
non-restraining is a very very
fragile and relative peace you get from
the life
even when when there's nothing you know
no great misfortune everything is fine
you're still never at ease completely
you can't be
but you want intuition that wants to be
these that everybody wants to there you are
that everybody wants to there you are
nobody will say no to ease
yeah you have to pay the thing
feed the thing exercise things will get
sick and you'll get grumpy yeah all you did
and you'll get grumpy yeah all you did
everything right
the vipers just get cranky sometimes
you're just a slave see they quickly
change sometimes they're completely
ignoring you
docile and then just snap
that's exactly what what the body is
what the health is what the life is what
the youth is where the strength is
it can just be swept away just changes
so it starts with those divine
messengers
sickness aging death but again
divine messenger means you recognize
that message as
as a future inevitability not like you
wait for it to become
inevitable reality to deal with it
because if you wait
to be sick aging and dying in order to
get rid of it it's too late
so to see that right now within this
life that currently nothing bothering me
everything is fine
that's that's exactly fine there's no
problem with that
now within that what is this life that
is fine
liable too
so do i ever say that yeah do you have a
controller well how much state you have
in
controlling the viper's mood and
behavior in action that's how much there
you have
none a divine message is like a divine
highlighter of the nature of what's good
divine reminder
this is yours the fact that
it's not right now happening doesn't
mean that you can avoid it
so what do you do well don't stop
avoiding it
keep it in the background of your mind
all the time that's like the mindfulness
of death
that the buddha praises the quickest way
but a bit dangerous as well
if you're not ready but yeah so whatever
you do
good joyful whatever just keep the
context that you might be dead within the next
that you might be dead within the next
in and out breath
then you you will be unable to enjoy
that delightful central sense you still
do things
you still eat think about like like you
you have
this person with people who are on death
row about to be executed in the states
about to be executed in the states
and then they were given the last meal
yeah whatever you want literally
whatever you want
and they would come with this like
insane sort of menu
would you enjoy it doesn't matter it
doesn't matter what they bring you
the nice is the taste is for literally
you you're about to get killed
so that cannot not be on your mind
so how would you relate to that meal
when you cannot shake off
the background of impending death
that's mindfulness of death if you would
but if you cultivate it not if you're
just subjected to it against your will
and you're still trying to like resist
in it internally
if you actually practice like that yeah
you would basically
fade away all the delight in no time or
go mad in the process of doing so
as many monks did in the suttas the ones
they were not ready
so the buddha's like okay well if you're
not ready maybe you know tony down a bit
but don't feel excused
on account of well the buddha said it's
fine to tony down well no
he said it's fine to take a different
approach but you're still at a perilous
shore so the outcome of that mindfulness of
so the outcome of that mindfulness of
death still needs to be developed one
way or the other
so it's actually you should be even with
more sense of urgency because
mindfulness is the quickest way
now you're choosing the non-quickest way
because you can't handle the quickest
way so now you should be twice as careful
so now you should be twice as careful
because you will have you're spending
more time in a dangerous shore
so having that context of death yeah
danger you can't engage in sensuality to you
you can't engage in sensuality to you
know to the extent of their delight you
can't but and even that by the way even if if
but and even that by the way even if if
you were to engage with sensuality
to give into the intention okay i'll do
this quickly or something
even to that momentary extent you need
to willingly choose to ignore the
context of death
if you willingly choose to not ignore
the context of death you will not be
able to engage with centrality
even if you decided to engage with
centrality say you decide to engage with
sexuality i will leave this
the most central dinner that they
prepared for me
or any other central satisfaction but
i'll be killed immediately after that
i will be brutally murdered
so even if you choose to engage with it
the only way you can do that is to
ignore the fact that you'll be brutally
murdered right after because if you
don't ignore it
none of that will be have any appeal
literally he's tasteless tasteless yeah
joyless but that's what i mean that
joylessness that's frightening and like
when people did kind of get a glimpse of
what the buddha was teaching they're
well they will kill me they will destroy
me that is just like utter
that's the worst nibbana you teach and
they would fall down on the ground in
despair hey oh my god that's horrible but
hey oh my god that's horrible but
it's horrible not because it's horrible
in itself it's horrible because of your
expectations of the gratuitous joy
and the light if you don't depend on it
joylessness is great it's non-disturbing
it's easy you're invisible to it it's
not harmful it's not dangerous
yeah there's passion but from the point
of your passion
this passion is the worst possible thing
like an addict
uh trying to give up heroin
the addiction
all the reason won't help him it's still
the most horrible thing he can imagine
being without this
like what will the life be without this
it's it's just it's too it's too
depressing to think about it
but not because the life will in itself
be bad it's just because of your
virtuously built up amplified
assumptions and expectations that you
can equally undo
or other people loved ones die say you
have to now readjust to the world
without that which was always there
taken for granted
as yours for you and so on
but the only reason you need
readjustments is because you yourself
drifted away from the reality of things
so the sooner you accept that the sooner
you readjust
and sensuality is that drifting away
from every time
every time it's it's perversion of
reality as the world would say so
both putting second is first then first
to second
distorting yourself you will you're
already aligning yourself with the right
order of things
and you're already revealing the nature
of that sensuality
that is it's pressuring and dragging you
around and
you're an addict already you're being
mindful of death
so again when i say mindfulness doesn't
mean like whatever thought pops up in
your mind you know
i'm assuming that think that no no
background context of death
means you don't have to think about it
just don't forget about it
have it in the back of your mind oh i'm
sitting here i'm drinking i'm getting up
i want to have some water maybe
and i might die by the end of this day i
might die by the meal i might die by the
end of this breath
oh that's a beautiful mountain that's a
beautiful river yeah and i might die by
the end of this breath
so maintaining the context means
if you're able to maintain the context
means you you're beginning to contrast
everything against that ultimate
inevitable context
and that's how you lose this enchantment
with these things because you're
enchanting with them because you don't
have the right contrast
there is a there is a common idea
that if i keep the context of death in
mind that i will enjoy life more right
that i will enjoy life more right
because remember you will die
sure so now we'll so that will be the
result of that context of the day but
that's not that
no that's not like you don't really see
that death pertaining because death
pertains to you right now
when those people think that they think
of death in 20 30 years time
which doesn't pertain to them it's an
imaginary idea of that
no he doesn't know but i might die
literally next second oh
then you feel it and then you will not
oh let me go and quickly do many things
no but i might literally dive in before
i start doing these things
yeah you want to get it real close well
you really want to make it pertain to
you but as i said you should only do it if
but as i said you should only do it if
you have been keeping the precepts
being well restrained not pursuing
centrality because if you jump into it
it will crush you like a little bug
just anxiety would be too overwhelming
and happen to the monks in the past
happened to the
contemporary times i mean i met number
of them many of them like
lost their minds and this robe there was
the best case scenario but yeah like because
best case scenario but yeah like because
it's it's play with fire
that can quickly burn all the classes or
completely incinerate you in the process
of doing so and the whole suta was when
all those monks went and jumped off the
cliffs and
got that man to kill them because they
were so disgusted with it and the death
and that
and then they would expect what happened
well you know that contemplation you
gave us
killed half of the monks they couldn't
handle it and said okay well then
do mindfulness of breathing instead if
you can't handle it which still results
in the same we spoke about that in other talks